all right everybody
we are back it is the jack murphy live
podcast and we are doing it live today
and uh my guest today is michael anton
he is a former national security council
uh officer for
donald trump a speechwriter an author an
all-around
flamethrower the penman of the infamous
famous flight 93 essay
uh michael i am so glad to have you
thank you so much for joining us
thank you all right fantastic so
uh as we were talking about before i
kind of like to give the audience a
little bit of a background on our guests
so that we can appreciate the context
uh of the book and that's what we're
gonna be talking about today is his new
book
i'll show it to you right now new book
the stakes
america at the point of no return
and if you guys think that title is a
hint at what is to come there is
is definitely the case uh it is very
spicy and we're going to get into it but
michael can you give us just a little
bit of background
uh i'd like to know sort of you know
your recent history how you got the
trump administration and cetera and we
could talk about that for a few minutes
um well my recent history is i'm a
lecturer
and a research fellow at hillsdale
college in washington so basically a
college professor who didn't finish his
phd so they can't call me a professor
um and what we do in washington is uh
undergraduate students who are at the
main campus in michigan
they can apply to spend a semester in
washington get an internship
take their courses at night i teach
undergrads i taught them last night and
then we have a new school relatively new
school
um that where we're awarding master's
degrees to
students who live in washington have
full-time jobs you know
can't afford to or just don't want to
get off the career track to quit and go
move somewhere and go to
school for a couple years but they want
to learn extra and get a degree
and so they can do that at night and i'm
teaching in that program as well so
that's that's what i've been doing since
i left the trump administration in
the spring of 2018.
how did you uh get into the trump
administration what was the
circumstances sort of preceding that and
uh what was your role there and then
yeah okay i got into it so i was on the
george w bush i was in the george w bush
administration for his
his entire first term and a little bit
into the second
and most of that time i spent on the
national security council staff in the
white house
and i left i went into corporate america
thinking you know i you know the way
the way careers people typically do you
work in government while you're young
you know when you want to have kids and
you get a bigger house you go into the
private sector and you never look back
right unless you get so rich that you
could but i wasn't thinking of what i
was doing i was like okay that was fun i
did it now
i'm gonna do something else trump came
along and
i you know at first i thought
this is the third time he's run for
president he's never serious he won't
follow through
i'm not paying attention to this i'm
just not gonna fall for it right and
then you know he's
talking about immigration which i was
very concerned about he's just talking
about things that i cared about and i
thought
well it's too bad he's not going to stay
in it because we need a candidate like
this but
you know whatever and then he stays in
it for a while
and i thought okay and he kept telling
people i'm not dropping out i'm in it
i'm gonna win it
so by about october november i start to
believe okay maybe he's serious
and i pitched an article to the
claremont review of books which
is published by my grad school thesis
advisor charles kessler
or publishes edited by i should say and
with whom i have been writing in its
entire
run print run and i never had an article
rejected
and i said i want to write the piece
saying trump should be the nominee this
is before votes are cast
you know the the case for trump he
should be the nominee
and charles said uh interesting send it
in so i wrote it it was
as long as like a typical crb article
from me 5000 words like that i sent it
in
and unusually it took about a month
for him to get back to me and then and
then said we're not gonna do it
and i thought hmm that's you know
disappointing so another guy i knew had
had a similar experience where he'd
written for a magazine
not a not a pro-trump piece but just an
explanation of trump
but but because it wasn't anti-trump it
sounded pro-trump right
he published that he followed up with a
really serious analysis of trump through
the lens of managerialism which is this
idea from james burnham's book from 1946
the managerial revolution which is on a
shelf back there somewhere i don't know
exactly where
um and the same magazine rejected that
so he and i happened to be at a dinner
one night
complaining saying these conservative
magazines are lame
they won't take any you know it's just
the usual nonsense
and he the next day founds a blog called
the journal of american greatness
and the anchor pieces of jag were my
rejected piece from crb and his rejected
piece from the weekly standard
and from there we blogged for about four
months we picked up a couple you know we
had some other people in on it and it
was a small group of people
and it got so big so fast that everybody
we all had a day job and most of us if
not all of us had day jobs whom
if they knew we were pseudonymously
blogging in favor of trump would have
been displeased
and so once peggy noonan wrote about it
in the wall street journal
the group consensus was take it down so
he took it down
and then wait what did she say that made
you guys she wrote about it no it was
favorable but it just
it shot the traffic on the thing up so
high
and it was you know it was sort of a
power line and you know
it's climbing and it's climbing it's
climbing then it gets in the wall street
journal and it just goes right up
gotcha and that's when everybody went
too much attention
right uh this was fun while it lasted
um so i thought that's it i did it i'm
never gonna do it again i'm going to
keep working
keep my head down and then over as the
summer wore on i just got
but oh you were asking how i got on the
campaign so
in the middle while jag was going i got
invited to a dinner
a book dinner for someone who wrote a
basically a kind of a pro-trump book on
your zoning this is a
it's frank buckley he's a professor at
the scalia law school here in northern
virginia
and it seemed like a lot of people
around the table it's like 15 people at
this dinner
a lot of people around the table they
knew what jag was and they knew that i
was one of the guys behind it but there
was just a kind of
agreement not to mention it right
because i was supposed to be hidden
and i appreciate it and i talked to
frank and he said you know i'm doing
work on the transition and you have this
experience with the nfc you want to help
us out
sure so he gets me involved in the
transition
and then i'm kind of quietly involved in
the transition
you know leave aside the flight 93
election which came out in september
of 2016. i was involved in the
transition and we did a lot of work
and then there was and then trump
surprisingly wins the election
lisa surprised me me too a lot of people
tell me like i knew he was going to win
i was like okay i didn't know he was
going to win
um and you know i had been sort of i did
all this work on the transition over the
summer
and then going into the fall campaign
like i got they made some changes and i
got frozen out
and i thought oh oh well whatever and
then right after
trump wins they came in and they
immediately fired all the guys that had
replaced the people i knew and they
put pence at the head of the transition
and a bunch of people i didn't know and
all of a sudden i was back in
right poof i'm in the transition again
and
start helping them do work on things and
you know
ended up getting that job i mean even
that was in a way a fluke
i didn't expect it to happen but i got
it and so i went in
with the administration at the beginning
mike flynn hired me
and uh i was with mike flynn for what 24
days until he got
shamefully railroaded out of there by
that corrupt process that's still going
on and
and unjustly torturing him yeah let's um
couldn't
we drill down on that for a second what
is your take on the real reason
that flynn got ousted
i think the best take is i think it's
two things
so my reason and i believe both these
reasons i'm just going to state them
because
one doesn't want my original reason the
other one is andy mccarthy's reason but
i think andy's right
my reason is part of it it was revenge
from the deep state for all the ways
that flynn had tortured them
especially in the obama administration
told them things that they didn't want
to hear
was on the right side of things when
they weren't and made them look bad when
he was proved right and they just were
they hate i mean remember barack obama
said one of the few things he said to
donald trump
in the oval office at that famous
meeting after the election
a few days after the election is you
can't trust mike flynn he's he named
mike flynn to the to the president-elect
and said you shouldn't hire that guy
the president of course didn't listen
and what were those things that
what were those things that he was right
on that they were wrong about i have
some ideas but i'm interested to hear
your take
it was mainly the iran deal stuff that
was a big part of it
um you know flynn was saying they're
lying about this they're doing this
you're giving them credit for
you know having refrained from x and y
and z and it's all it's all a sham and
you're trying to put this over on the
american people
and some of it's just threat assessments
of stuff going on in the middle east
and and you know and some of it had to
do with
i used to remember this more clearly
because i remember one of one of the
things that got me the job with flynn
as i went into that job interview the
most prepared i'd ever been in my life
and so if you want to hear this like i
had been
working with people on the transition i
still hadn't met flynn um
and the first time i met him like i got
this meeting and they said okay
basically you're on you know you
this is the job you want you you can you
got your meeting
and i spent all this time preparing and
i wrote a speech for him
just said this is how you're going to
introduce yourself to the world
this is or to reintroduce yourself this
is the communications plan for the
administration's you know
for you and here's one for the
administration and here's a memo on how
the structure ought to work and
all of this stuff that i had prepared
and i walked in there i think my meeting
was at three
and at like one o'clock that day they
announced that they had given that job
to somebody else
and i was so bummed i was like i don't
even know why i even go to the meeting
and somebody said no just go you never
know what might happen
i said okay and i walked in there and he
says oh great to meet you i've heard all
these great things i know you've been
helping us out
you know since july or whatever um and i
i still haven't met you so i'm happy to
and he said uh so what what is it that
you're looking at this white board
with the you know the wiring diagram or
whatever you call those
you know the diagrams with the positions
and who reports to whom up there
he goes he walks over the whiteboard
like what is it that you're looking for
and i go
that one which you gave away two hours
ago therefore i'm not here to ask you
for anything i'm here i'm santa claus
today this was like
you know getting we're getting close to
christmas this is early december i think
i go i'm santa claus here are some gifts
and i give him like here's the speech i
wrote here here's a communications plan
here's
this there's this and he just like sits
down and which is the two of us alone in
a room in trump tower
and he just starts looking over the
paper he doesn't say anything i'm like
five minutes go by 10 minutes go by
maybe 15 minutes go by and he looks up
and he goes
i've got to find a way to get you on my
team i said
okay what do you want to do he walks
back over to the white whiteboard and we
worked out this kind of role
over you know a couple of weeks that i
was going to do and then the person who
had accepted the job that i was
had angled for had to withdraw and then
they immediately just said okay we're
putting you in that box
i'm all right nice would you would you
consider just get back to your earlier
question the other reason i want to get
rid of him which is important
mccarthy is the one who fleshed this
theory out i think he's right
is they realized they were only going to
get away with the russia hoax
they had to get rid of flynn because he
understood how the intelligence process
worked how the dia worked out all this
stuff worked
and if he was there he would have caught
them he would have warned the president
i think that's reasonable i i also think
it's reasonable that uh
flynn might have been one of the more
perfectly suited people to work with
trump would you consider
uh flynn to be our kind of woke
um you know in certain ways yes in
certain ways not i mean
you know for so i was a bit closer
you know on the issues to flynn in a
certain way like a lot of my friends
you know very very pro-trump friends who
are very interested in foreign policy
if anything they think you know they're
always worried about neocon influence
and
hawks you know hawkishness this flynn
was more hawkish than they would have
wanted
right i mean the ideal national security
candidate for some of our
more maga type friends is douglas
mcgregor
you know somebody like that who's now
the nominee ambassador to germany
um flynn was absolutely no neocon
you know democracy spreading you know
war for democracy type but he was a
he was willing to be a little bit more
elbow-throwing with american power
wherein when he thought
national interest required it and he was
very in tune with trump on that very in
tune with trump on that
um so i think they would have made a
great team had they been able to
stay together and and i would have i
still would have liked to have seen
what mike flynn could have done in that
role you know when you have
24 days and you're just being literally
harassed
extra legally by the fbi and the justice
department the whole time
you can't you can't show any part of
what you can do yeah
yeah tragedy how did your time in the
white house work out
did you have any accomplishments you're
proud of anything that
you regretted and then uh how did it
wrap up i mean i got
lots of regret i mean i don't know how
much your listeners will care about this
and they'll probably call me a neocon
for it which is fine i've been called
worse
um the one thing that i got done that
would not have gotten done otherwise
is the obama you know when the when the
raid on bin laden's compound happened
um they gathered up a ton of
intelligence all of which was analyzed
and
very little of which by the time the
obama administration was over very very
little of that was put out
even though everything exploitable about
it you know had been
and so they just decided they're not
going to put it out and the reason they
didn't want to put it out is because it
showed that they were
they were basically lying about a lot of
stuff and i got in there and i had some
you know it's like
i'd known the issues and i was like i
want to make it a priority to get this
out
and i started talking early on to people
and finally i just went up to
pompeo in the sit room one day you know
he he knew me slightly he didn't know me
very well and i said look
he was the director of the cia that was
like there's no reason not to put this
out if there's something in there that
you have to redact redact it that's fine
right we don't want to blow any live
assets or anything like that but
let's get this stuff out there and the
only reason the obama people didn't put
it out is because
it showed how disingenuous they were
being about the iran deal among other
things
and finally you know we shook that loose
i don't think that would have happened
i'm not saying i'm the only one who did
it but i don't think it would have
happened had i not been there
um but otherwise you know this is this
sounds like such a cop
out so be it like my job wasn't to do
accomplishments
right my job make sure the president got
credit for his accomplishments
right and that's you know that's what i
tried to do
yeah i mean that's that's what that's
what people do when they're working for
somebody that they like and respect you
know it's uh
you sort of pass that that that credit
up the chain
um how did uh how did your time there
come to an end
um well i left the week i mean
h.r mcmaster left on a friday
and um bolton was coming in on a monday
and i was prepared to just leave when
mcmaster left
in part because like i didn't want to
audition for a third nap you know what i
mean i had auditioned for my job once
flynn hired me flynn's gone i'm stunned
they hire somebody i
i don't know and have never met who uh
had me kind of on a
probation for three months before you
decided you're okay you can stay
and i remember at one point saying to
because i still had owned a house in
house in new york and i was taking the
train home on the weekends
those weekends when i could i hadn't
moved my family hadn't sold my house
and at one point i got kind of
exasperated and i said to mcmaster look
if you're going to fire me fire me
that's cool
i'll just go home but but damn it
i don't want to sell my house and move
down here and get fired after that so
you need to let me know if i'm staying
or not staying and i'll make this
decision and he laughed he's like no
you're okay you could you stand so i
sold my house i moved down here
you know i figured i'd be there as long
as he was there or maybe if they
transitioned to somebody
well he gets um
he they actually had a kind of an
amicable party in a way like it was
interesting you know they never
he and trump never gelled never got
along that well um or
there were moments when they did and
there were moments when they didn't but
overall the relationship kind of got off
to a rocky start and it never became
what trump had with flynn
forged over the course of the campaign
and
you know he called mcmaster at one point
and said i'm gonna make a switch
but you know you have x number of weeks
and mcmaster was around for a long time
after that and in the meetings and doing
his job
and the president was very gracious
toward him uh
during all that time and i sort of
decided i was gonna leave and several
people in the white house
said um you know don't no you you you
should stay
uh i need you know uh people told me
they needed me to stick around um
you know sarah sanders in particular
said i need you to stick around because
you have really big help on
all the stuff there's all this stuff
coming up this summer the north korea
summit all these things that i always
use you on
said youtube there's a chance it's it's
a decent chance that
i won't be able to so um
basically i found out the you know the
day before
that i was just gonna get summarily
fired
in the morning by john bolton who i you
know looked me in the eye the friday
before and
let's just say at least misled me and
misled sarah when she asked him if he
was going to make changes and he said no
and she said in particular i need
michael anton and he said i only have
this small
front office staff that i'm bringing in
and i'm not going to be making any other
changes and so
and at this point you know i was a kind
of agnostic to slightly favorable on
john bolton
i thought i think he's too hawkish for
the president but he's also
a very um staunch defender of american
sovereignty against creeping
internationalism
uh you know unilateralism these kinds
there's there's a lot of places where
they clearly align and there are places
where they don't align
but he's also a master bureaucratic
infighter whom i saw
in the bush administration and i saw how
he knows how to work the levers of
bureaucratic power
and that was a talent that the trump
administration at that time and i think
still to this day
it doesn't entirely lack but it it lacks
relative to other republican
administrations it's
very hard to get something done in
washington especially as a republican
if you don't know how to play that grand
pipe organ that is the federal
bureaucracy and he knew how
he knows how so i thought you know okay
i certainly had no personal animus
for him i do now
but that's his fault and he he sought
that and he got he got what he asked for
so i resigned to the president that
night that sunday night
and said yeah the president was
extremely gracious come see me tomorrow
and i went into the office
um that was my last day in the office
except one and i hung out with the
president in the oval for a little bit
and he was very very nice about it
and then you know a couple weeks later i
went and i cooked at state dinner i
don't know if you know that story if you
saw it new york times
um yeah so i'm an amateur
cook and i went to culinary school for
fun and i used to work in a restaurant
for free for fun and then i kind of hung
it up and i you know i hadn't done it in
a while and i thought you know it would
be cool to be to cook in the white house
kitchen so at one point i asked um
stephanie grisham who was then the first
lady's comms director who's now
the first lady's chief of staff i think
you know can she so they run them they
run the white house kitchen like i
actually have a background doing this
i'm good at it like i think they'd let
me just
work on the line down there one day and
she said i'll ask the chef
chef brought me down and interviewed me
had me work on the governor's dinner in
like february then she says well we'll
need we
we could use you at the state dinner
which was going to be april 24th well i
left the white house by then so my last
request to john kelly
as i left was i said oh by the way you
know general because they're they're
they're like negotiating with you this
is when you have to give your pass back
this is when you have to do this
and this and i said can i keep my hard
pass until
the 24th i'll turn it in the next days
like why i said well i'm supposed to
cook on the line at the state dinner and
he looked at me like i was crazy i just
got this look any five minutes like i'm
and i kind of tell him the story and
he's still looking at me and he goes
yeah i mean okay fine come in and cook
like what it just took him a while to
process the weirdness of the request
yeah that is that's a good anecdote i
like that but
all in all it just sort of seems like
what could have been uh with flynn
and you in the white house doing work
for at least one term uh
what could have been in that regard it
might have been yeah and i got a
statement shout out to kt mcfarland who
was a really good deputy
and brandon ran a tight dc and also
really got trump in a way i mean that's
another regret that i have is a number
of us
tried to persuade mcmaster to keep kt
because we thought first of all she was
good and second of all
she had the kind of relationship with
trump that he didn't have and probably
was never gonna have
and said you know she's going to be
useful
in in many ways but in one one of those
ways will be
as a kind of medium between you and the
president and
he just had this thought that like no no
you know he's i'm an officer i got to
pick my own exo and
so i i think you know he
who knows mcmaster might have survived
longer had he had he kept kt around
never know fascinating well we're going
to see how that all
plays out when we look back in the
history books but let's move on a little
bit
um you uh are
did are you a claremont fellow is that
right yeah i mean
my primary affiliation is i'm a lecturer
at hillsdale college's washington dc
campus
um but i'm also a senior fellow at the
claremont institute and i was educated
at the claremont graduate school in the
mid 90s when the sort of the
patron saint if you will of the
claremont institute harry jaffa was
alive
he was retired um he was an emeritus
professor so he wasn't actively teaching
but
you know i hung around with him like
almost every day for three years and
then
charles kessler who's still on the
faculty there was my main grad advisor
and i worked for the claremont institute
uh part-time my entire three years when
i was in grad school
and i've always been affiliated with it
since then well
i had the pleasure of speaking with ryan
williams for a while we did a podcast
together
uh several months ago and in talking to
him and just sort of observing things
um and in reading your book it does seem
that there's been sort of a transition
or there's one in the works at claremont
uh is that something you can speak to
maybe
like yeah i get this a lot i actually i
had this conversation with somebody the
other day
and just again today where
you know people say you guys have
changed or you pre anton have changed
where the institute has changed
and i said no i don't maybe maybe in
terms of emphasis tone
tactics right but i can build my
entire case for whatever it is i'm
talking about for trump
for this new book within the four walls
that i learned from harry java i don't
consider myself to have departed from
jaffa's teaching or claremont orthodoxy
whatever that is one iota
now joppa himself could be imprudent in
his
um in the moment political judgment so
for instance in 1994 my first year in
claremont there was a ballot initiative
in california called proposition 187
the simple made a simple point that we
are not going to give welfare benefits
to illegal aliens emergency room care
sure
you know but like public assistance
welfare no
and this was a ballot initiative it
passed 60 40. so it's overwhelmingly
positively received of course
immediately invalidated by a federal
judge and never implemented
but um jaffa was against it
and he had his right his rationale was
muddled
and what i found interesting is all of
his students
were for it all the rest of the
claremont people were at the whole
institute all of jaffa students the
claremont diaspora or whatever you want
to call it
was perfectly okay with it but the old
man
had a problem and we all thought yeah
that's just him being
prudent again but we know that this is
okay and that this is completely
consistent with everything that we
believe
so i feel that same way about you know
we have claremont has certain some what
i call
our we have our concern trolls people
who think they understand us better than
we understand ourselves and they like to
discuss on twitter or wherever in some
liberal magazines and say
there goes the claremont institute
supporting this thing that it shouldn't
they've lost their way it's so sad to
see
and i just like give me a break yeah but
that's not the angle that i'm taking
here i'm not being i'm not being
critical
i'm looking at sort of like a
generational shift it's definitely look
it's younger there's a new you know
i i'm getting to be one of the old guys
in the room now where
ryan is i think 38 and matt is uh you
know matt and james are
40 or 41 and arthur miller who's just
hired i think it's 32 or 30. so there's
definitely been
a changing in the guard in terms of the
people running it they're younger
but all educated in the same tradition
and you know he went to the same
principles
yeah well it's interesting to see
the recent fellowship fellow classes
uh as well as some of the the literature
that uh the
um uh review the book review has taken
on incl
including bronze age pervert with bronze
aid mindset um
i was that's a little bit of doing i
remember
um i told the story in the review but
you know helen andrews who's now running
the american conservative
emailed me and she said you know this
guy yarvin
wants to meet you and i said does he you
know he was internet famous at the time
and i was kind of a nobody so i thought
does he know who i am she goes of course
that's why he wants to meet you so we
arranged to have a dinner at my house
and he brings me his book
he literally i didn't say this in the
review but he literally when he
pulled it out of his like you know
bicycle messenger bag he held it up over
his head like this
and he said behold bronze age mindset
and
he gave me the book and i looked through
it i'm going uh
yeah thanks uh well very nice to meet
you and i put it aside
looked at it a couple days later my wife
said to me have you looked at that thing
and i said no not yet
it's like a weird kind of comic book
nietzsche without pictures
it's really weird so i started reading
it and i thought
this is stupid and then beating
who was you know a former writer he
texted me and i mentioned i go have you
heard of this thing and he goes oh yeah
it's great you have to read it
i said really you gotta read it now so i
once i
really sat down to read it i got into it
and i had fun with it it's a fun book
whatever you think of it it's a fun book
to read
and you know one night bees texted me
and he said
you should review it for the crb lol and
i just texted back lol because
you know my first thought is that's
impossible and then i thought like
is it really and about three weeks later
charles kessler who's my again who's the
editor of the crb
and his wife whom i've known for years
is the president of a think tank in san
francisco and they held their annual
dinner and the guest
of honor was tucker carlson and since i
know tucker and was writing about him
for the crb right at that moment
they had me fly out and i went to the to
this dinner
you know hung out with tucker and
charles but i pinned charles aside at
the reception and
because i'm part of my deal with the
claremont institute as a senior fellows
i'm supposed to write
for every crb issue and i said charles i
and
you know mostly i come up with my ideas
but sometimes charles says i want you to
do this
i said i know what i want to do next i
want to review a book called brahms
and here we are like a cocktail
reception at a hotel in san francisco
for this annual dinner and there's 200
donors
and you know 300 500 i don't know it was
big tucker really draws a crowd
and i i said i want to review a book
called bronze age mindset
you know kessler is very debonair gives
me this look like and what is that and i
try to explain to him
what it is and why i think it's worth
doing it kind of hurt me out
but usually it's like a quick yes or
what this was a i'll think about it
and then i wrote up some further emails
explaining what i was trying to do and
he's like
okay and then i felt like it would be
spicy enough that hillsdale might think
what what is
this guy doing so i had to explain to
people hillsdale this is what i'm doing
and this is why i'm doing
it and they kind of okay
um but that was funny it was funny like
talk you know
i mean i feel like that i'm too old for
the book right it's not written i'm 50.
there's no the book is not written for
me in any in any sense whatsoever
so like if you're having to talk to
people ten or a dozen years older than
you about why it's valuable
it feels if it feels weird to me it's
even weirder for them
yeah i had bronze age pervert on the
podcast immediately after yearbook
review so we had plenty to
talk about that uh and i i would say
maybe it is for you i think i find a lot
of bronze age perverts writing echoed
i mean not specific not directly but i
see similarities in some of the issues
that you raised especially you know this
strong focus on the elites and his bug
men
and and near the end of the book you
start talking about the need for
uh sort of an updated masculinity and
carving out space for
for for boys to be rough and to fight
and learn trades and shoot and study the
great works which is
basically the exact same prescription
there
uh at the end of bronze age pervert as
well but
i think it's just uh kudos to you for
taking that on kudos to claremont for
publishing it
uh kicking off that dialogue that went
around with yarvin and you and others as
well i thought that was fantastic and
and that to me is sort of the angle on
the the claremont evolution that i
that i was looking at yeah i mean at the
end this is what i said in my review
at the end of the day i'm still a
claremont guy which means i'm still with
the founders
and and i found it impossible
that i mean he only responded to me one
time and i found it impossible to
pin back down on this question of
equality right so is
equality has come to be a swear word
on the right or at least for certain
people on the right who think it just
leads to
leveling it just leads to the neoliberal
order
and you know drugging everybody out and
seeing them on the cow all of these
terrible things
and you know the way i was taught it uh
by jaffa by tom west by charles kessler
and by the founders themselves by
reading their books
you know it equality properly understood
by the american founders leaves all
kinds of room for human excellence
and flourishing and also requires
certain virtues that they absolutely
admit are not evenly distributed
throughout the human population
is everybody courageous is everybody
equally courageous for instance
obviously not you but you cannot fight
and win an american revolution without
courageous men and courageous men are
sort of in this baptian
spirit in a certain way but i didn't
find any
you know i i didn't pin back down on
this question and i don't know what his
ultimate answer is but i think his
ultimate answer at the end of the day is
that all men are not created equal
right whereas my my ultimate answer at
the end of the day is in the decisive
sense in which the founders meant it all
men are still created equal
and that is that's a philosophic gap
that i don't think he and i will ever be
able to bridge
honestly i feel like you guys are
talking past each other on that subject
as a matter of fact i think you kind of
see things the same way
just sort of discussing uh you're
debating the intent of the text
at the time yeah and and rather
than uh this notion of are people
different no he strongly
he strongly believes that as well you
know i tried to get that across in the
review that i think you know
um a lot of him a lot of his deliberate
outrages are just sort of two-by-fours
to the to the cranium
rhetoric like you know i i teach i i
teach machiavelli and i've studied my
valley more than i've studied any other
political philosopher
and he really smacks you with a lead
pipe frequently with
outrageous things that if he meant them
completely seriously you'd have to just
conclude this is an evil man
right maybe he means it kind of in a
certain way and i
gave a playful interpret i thought it
was a playful interpretation of baptist
endorsement of piracy
seeing how he would respond to that um
and i don't know he seems to me from
what i
have seen of his writings elsewhere to
be sort of all in on piracy
and my response to that is i really got
kicked in the teeth by a lot of his fans
when i said this in my
response to his response like like
piracy like really
because eventually it you know we could
get to this this is a theme of my book
right which is
yeah whatever you want to call it the
neoliberal order the liberal
international order the current
arrangement you know uh woke capital all
of these things
i call it neoliberalism just because
it's a kind of a word everybody
become a common usage if the if the
oligarchs who run it can't keep it going
then and then it crashes what comes next
and i have some ideas about
what may come next and perhaps some
ideas about what ought to come next
and you know pirates in fortresses on
the edge of the world doesn't seem to
seems to me to be kind of comic book-y
and also not the basis for a sound
political order going forward which
means you know either that's kind of
joking about that for a rhetorical
effect or he
and i just don't sort of see the future
the same way i don't i don't honestly
know the answer
i don't think he answered it because i
don't think he wanted to answer that
question
probably i see parallels in that with
your discussion at the city state which
we're going to get to uh that's one of
the possible outcomes there but um
that was a good time i appreciate you
doing that really sincerely it's
i think it's good for i think it was
good to con
create a bridge between some of the
older guard
and the newer guard who may not see
things exactly the same way
but clearly i see the problems that was
the main point of reviewing the book was
to say look
we used to be able to reach 25 year old
21 year olds and 25 year olds with a
certain message in say 1980 or 19
even up to 1995 that hits with a thud
now
it hit and you know those of us in our
50s and 60s who
are still preaching the old-time
conservative religion we could be right
in every particular but at a minimum we
have to admit that our rhetorical
strategy
is failing and come up with something
else and i wasn't saying copy this guy i
would say you need to be aware
that this is a hit it's the same way
like if you're trying to produce movies
or records and you don't know what's
popular in your target audience right
now
you're going to fail right it doesn't
matter if you like it you got to know
what's going to work uh it doesn't
matter it doesn't even matter if that's
not the specific thing that you're
trying to copy you at least need to know
what it says and have some sense of why
it's popular
if you don't know that you're not gonna
get anywhere that's what that's
fundamentally why i wrote the review it
wasn't for
you know it was it was for my generation
and older
right it was for me the people it was
from my generation and for the people
who taught us
i was trying to bring them news that
they otherwise wouldn't have had
noble i'm trying to do the same here i'm
not sure
half of my audience may be familiar with
your work but they will be
moving forward one last question about
claremont
and rhetoric uh
strauss leo strauss has written about uh
how the philosopher must write in order
to deal with
politicians um is what influence did
that have on you in writing this book
how
how between the eyes are you yeah
it refers to i mean it's one of
strauss's great themes but the
the book in which he treats this
thematically at the greatest length is
called persecution and the art of
writing
and this theory is known as esoteric
writing and it's the thing for which
strauss was
the most ridiculed in his lifetime
uh and still straussians are ridiculed
for it and his basic point is
he uses the metaphor of reading reading
between the lines
right um sorry turned this off that's a
lamb line for you kids out there
i know i know i know um it's come it's
been it's been a godsend in the past
couple of days because uh i've done so
much radio and it sounds
way better on the landline all um right
so
fundamentally you write for two audi an
esoteric writer writes for two audiences
there's a surface which everybody reads
and then there's a depth which only the
few
can tease out um and and uh
so your question to me is to what extent
do i do that
um i mean it's self-defeat if i let me
put it this way
if i did it it's it defeats the purpose
of esotericism to admit that you did
in some cases there are examples of
esoteric books that say at the beginning
this is an esoteric book but then they
don't tell you how
so maimonides guide of the perplexed
says
the book is sealed with seven seals
montesquieu at the beginning of the
spirit of the laws says it may look like
this has no
design or order but there's a design and
a structure there and if you find that
you will find
the intent of the author but then he
doesn't tell you what it is you have to
find it right
and there are other types of esoteric
books that just
seem to be complete like my
maybe my favorite apart from machiavelli
is xenophon who
also writes in greek i was a student of
socrates and a contemporary of plato
interestingly apparently they hated each
other
um plato thought that xenophon was a
dumb brute
kind of a big dumb jock and xenophon
thought plato was a
wordy snob this is according to diogenes
lyricist uh
both of them probably had a point um but
xenophon writes in this very simple kind
of
c-spot run greek you know just like so
simple that for a long time
people thought this can't possibly be
profound because
it's just too spare and too basic but
strauss sort of revived the study of
xenophon by showing ah no you if you
read it super carefully you'll realize
they're all these hidden debts so i
guess you could say there's two ways to
do esotericism you know one is to
announce upfront that you're doing it
but then leave to the reader to figure
out how you did it
and another is just to pretend you
didn't do it at all
all right we will leave it at that uh
let's get into the book guys the book
here
is let me pull it up again the stakes
america at the point of no return it was
just released
i believe last week go to
amazon and get it you're gonna want to
read it we're gonna talk all about it
right now
uh it opens up with us talking about
being afraid
what do we have to be afraid of michael
am i afraid are you afraid what should i
be afraid of
i kind of am i mean i'm um naturally
maybe
a bit of a nervous person so but what i
say we should be afraid of is blue state
politics from coast to coast the
entire united states becomes california
um
that should worry us because california
is not a happy place
it may be you know people think of it
well it's got great weather all these
wonderful natural resources and so on
it has that it has world-class
attractions and so on
but it's not what it i'm from california
my family
has been in california since my
ancestors emigrated to the united states
in the 19th century
we've never lived anywhere else in the
usa until i left i'm the first one to
ever leave
and um
it's become a kind of dystopia for the
middle class
um unaffordable horrible traffic
bad services high taxes crippling
regulation
it's just it you know you pay
dearly and get little um
the only people for whom california
really works are the super rich
for whom an upper middle class lifestyle
that costs let's say
x in the normal part of the united
states it costs
10 20 or 30 x in certain parts of
california
and it works for those at the very
bottom especially if they've fled
real serious poverty in another country
say central america
or the much or the very poor parts of
mexico
you know poverty and subsidized poverty
in california as
victor davis hanson put it seems
paradise compared to the
really hard um poverty in
in you know parts of in point south in
certain parts of the
uh uh uh central and latin america so
it works for those people the very very
rich and
in a certain way the very very poor and
it fails
everyone else and just also just vacuum
cleans them of resources
um and the state among other things is
incompetent i mean as we're seeing right
now
not the first time in recent history
that they can't keep the lights on
so they have to turn off the power
delivery it's one thing when
you know sometimes the power goes out
because uh a tree falls and it knocks
out a wire and sometimes it goes out you
know
a switching station or whatever blows
they deliberately will just shut down
the lights
um when rolling blackouts when demand
exceeds the capacity
so my poor my poor mother uh and
sometimes they tell you you know hey
your lights are going out and sometimes
they they don't like she'll be
sitting at home getting dinner ready and
you know about six o'clock just
everything shuts off and no light no
nothing you know
if you have an electric oven too bad and
she just sort of puts everything in the
fridge and goes and
writes a candle and reads a book and
waits you know sometimes they come on in
an hour sometimes they come back on in
six sometimes they come back on 12.
so there's so many things wrong with it
the whole first chapter
i call it um there's a famous anecdote
about oliver cromwell you know the man
who cut off
king charles the first of england's head
and ruled england as a
basically a dictator for 14 years i
think it was 14 years
um is it to his official painter he said
paint me warts and all and that's where
we get the phrase warts and all right
give me the full accurate portrait well
my portrait of california in chapter one
of the book is definitely a
an emphasis on the warts i admit that
the good stuff exists you know yosemite
valley
and san francisco bay and disneyland and
these things but
mostly now living in california is warts
i think if you actually have to live
work and pay taxes there and deal with
the commuting
and the infrastructure and the services
it is a bleak picture that you paint in
that first chapter and it makes me
wonder just
who are the americans living there
what is their concept of american
identity what
what is your concept of an american
identity is there an american
consciousness that binds us together as
a nation
no not anymore there's an american
consciousness that binds part of us
together
who think about cells as americans but i
think there's 2020 laid anything
completely bare there's a huge chunk of
america i don't i hope it's
not half i don't know how many it is but
there's a lot of people who say
america's evil america's fundamentally
bad it's fundamentally racist it's
not only is that you know not only a
1776 racist 1776 isn't even the founding
1619 is the founding
i commend to your readers by the way uh
a wonderful crb piece in the
a recent issue by richard samuelson on
the 1619 project and how he's a
historian and how they just it just gets
everything wrong
pile that on top of the critiques of it
by gordon wood
and sean wellins and other you know
extremely liberal left of center almost
leftist historians who have knocked the
1619 project
i quote in chapter eight of my book a
little book that came out when i was in
college in california
called the disuniting of america by
arthur schlesinger jr
he was you know a harvard guy harvard
educated
and eventually ended up uh in a very
distinguished chair at the city
university of new york
but you know famous for being one of jfk
speechwriters and white house aides
wrote the book a thousand days
you know a real wrote the book the age
of jackson and then the
you know a major liberal uh intellectual
of the 20th century
one of the most prominent and he wrote a
very little book in 1991 he could see
all of this wokeness coming
and deliberate dividing of people and
identity politics and so on and he said
we can't hold the country together if we
do this this is this is ridiculous we're
deliberately tr
trashing the civic culture we have that
keeps us together as a people
and it will break the country at some
point if we don't cool it and the book
got up
basically a positive reception in 1991.
unfortunately
as a the ruling class and the
intellectuals and everyone with power
um didn't heed his warnings at all and
we're now
pretty much exactly where he predicted
we would end up it took
you know i hard to say if it uh you know
we should be surprised it's happening
now that it didn't
if it didn't happen sooner or later
until 2020 you know my
my kind of thought was yeah i know where
this is all heading
but you know who knows what it might
have might be 10. you might be 20 years
might be 30 40. it could be a while
right well now we know the culture seems
to have really cracked and i don't know
i don't see how it gets put back
together anytime soon this year
right
if there's nothing was there ever
something that held us all together as
americans that was as
as binding of an experience as it is to
be french or to be chinese or to be
anybody else um i
think maybe i'm going to answer answer
this question yes or no
yes and no because you want to say as
much right
well maybe not as much because if you're
chinese you know
that chinese civilization is literally 5
000 years old
right and your ancestors on that soil
you may not know the names back more
than two three generations
go back millennia right and you're part
of a culture that's
gone through all kinds of now you know
china really only becomes china about 2
000 years ago as we know it
but that's still a long 2 000 years is a
long time uh
you know english the english have very
clear records of
monarchs and aristocracies and
parliamentary debates
and bill's been laws being passed going
back
you know almost a millennium too or if
not more than a millennium but you know
the magna carta is 12 15
for god's sake so not i don't think the
united states can be
can have a national identity that's as
deep rooted as
some of these other countries right but
did it have something like that that we
deliberately fractured
and by the way these some of these other
i mean the chinese are in better shape
than we are because as evil as their
leadership is in many ways they're not
dumb enough to deliberately
uh fracture the um national identity of
the
population whereas things aren't great
right now in the national cultures of
england or france i'd say england is
britain is worse off than france by by
some significant degree
but france has got its own problems and
i say that not to bash france i love
france but
we did put together this is chapter two
is all about this and it's the chapter
that i think i've gotten the most
criticism for
not because people well i've gotten two
criticisms for it one is people said
boring it reads like a master's thesis
or something and like
academic who cares um and then from the
right
i get oh that's anton trying to keep
civic nationalism alive when he should
know by now that it's totally dead
and there's no hope for it and i want to
say is first of all
is the problem that is the ditch that
we're in right now owing to civic
nationalism
and in part i answer that the founders
didn't have a choice they had to adopt
civic nationalism
right because the facts on the ground in
1776 as we form
the social compact with the declaration
of independence is the country is
already a multi-ethnic
society now it's not as multi-ethnic as
it is now but it wasn't like we could
just say
hey this is this is you know new england
and we're all english well
we got all these other it was already
pluralistically religious it was it had
a lot of
regional ethnic religious and other
differences
and it had to see englishness and
frenchness and chineseness and
japaneseness
come together over centuries and
millennia and nobody knows how it
happened
historians spend all their time you know
reading as many old books as they can
archaeologists go around and digging and
finding the roots of this and
find you know well wow look at this
building that
dates from 75 years before the earliest
dwelling we had ever found here before
right and they're trying to piece it
together
but in the case of all of those nations
nobody sits down
one you know in an assembly in
philadelphia or wherever one day and
says
we are splitting off from you and we are
becoming us
sign here right explicitly forms the
social compact all of a sudden we are as
the
first paragraph of the declaration of
independence says we are then one people
how do we bind those people together
well that's one of the ways that they
did it and it's not the only way
uh john jay says in federalist too
how lucky we are to be so alike
in our habits and sentiments right to uh
to cherish the same principles of
government to have similar ways of life
to have a similar type of religion
to have a common language right um and
we just fought the revolutionary war
nothing brings people together in a way
like
struggle does you it's the same story
you hear about these guys who haven't
seen each other
they see each other once a year for 50
years but like nine months in a combat
situation somewhere bombs them for life
so the revolutionary war did that for
the american people
so i get these critics to my right who
say
um american amer the idea of what it
means to be an american has become
so ridiculously abstract that you know
we just basically say everybody in the
in the world is a potential american and
so all you know we can we can invite
you know as many tens of millions of
people as we want and america is an idea
and all you have to do is accept the
idea and you're american and there's
nothing to america
and they say that's total hogwash and i
agree with him that is total hogwash
but they i wish my critics would be more
willing
to concede the fact that
um america the
the american way of doing it has worked
in the sense that like i
when i'm just take my own ancestors
right
uh of my eight great grandparents six
are italian one was greek and one was
lebanese
all of whom got here in a period between
about 1880 and 1910
initially um
neither myself nor any of my relatives
uh nor my children i
feel we're sick we're totally american
you know just completely totally
americanized welcomed into the social
compact
completely assimilated into the culture
in every way and like
that shows the success what america can
do when these processes are working and
i
can point to a lot of different people
um one of my teachers one of harry
jaffa's best students
uh he his father his parents got him out
of hungary in 1956 as the russians
rolled in
when he was 10 years old and he grew up
in hollywood you know
went to hollywood high the literal
hollywood high on hollywood
not yet i can't i think it's on sunset
boulevard anyway
uh where lana turner went you know and
was discovered at the soda fountain by a
talent scout and this stuff
peter schramm was his name he died a few
years ago right sram
born in hungary 10 years in hungary
learned perfect english learned amer
completely americanized by america
completely
his his old quip used to be that he was
born american but in the wrong place
right so if if i'm willing more than
willing because i think it's right and i
attack
those notions of america as an
abstraction i attack it pretty
vigorously in the book to say
yeah america is not just an idea there's
more to it than that but i wish the
people to my right who criticized me
would admit
america has been successful at doing
exactly the thing that they say
can't be done there was no way in 1770
like
if if the only way for nationhood to be
real
is uh centuries rooted ethnic identity
then you have to say the american
revolution was completely unjust and
shouldn't have happened and there should
never have been in america
now that's the left-wing position today
there should never have been in america
because america is fundamentally evil
if the right is going to be on the same
spot as the left on the question of the
existence and the justice of the
existence of america
then i gotta step back and say goodbye
to both of them
so one time you say there's not an
american
consciousness that binds us together
anymore
because the left has spent 50 years
hammering
away at it and fracturing it yeah just
smashing it right as exactly as what
arthur
schlesinger warned about there was about
halfway into the process when he wrote
that book
and now the process has been completed
except that i still say that there's
i don't know what it is there's 40
there's 50 percent maybe 60
of the population whatever it is i say
in the book somewhere that
you know it's in chapter two i do i say
the people that i'm speaking to are
people who identify
as american and only as american and
those people
exist by the tens of millions in this
country the problem is
that there are tens of millions who feel
the exact opposite and they control
all the commanding heights of discourse
power money
and so on i'm a little confused and i
pardoned me for being uh
elementary on this um no amount of
propaganda or
politicizing will change the ethnic
nature
of being chinese and china
propaganda and ideas and discourse
whatever you're saying
is chipping away and destroying what it
is to be
american so by that in my understanding
that this american consciousness
is a concept not
a blood a language a history
but really an idea i know
i think it's i think it's both right so
let's say
let's say one of the outcomes that i
outline in chapter seven comes to pass
right the left gets back into total
power
push the pedal to the floor crash the
system
and the american system ceases to
function
at some point in the in the future right
there will still be people alive on the
north american continent
granted unless they're seen on a real
pandemic that kills everybody or a
nuclear war or something people are
going to be alive here they're not going
to have a government they're going to
self-organize
they're going to start they're going to
do exactly what aristotle says people do
in the in the politics he says people do
which is they come together
to do jointly what cannot be done or
cannot be done well
alone right they're gonna do that now
i don't know about you if you let's just
pick any part of the country you want
montana idaho wisconsin michigan
tennessee
arkansas the texas panhandle the
oklahoma panhandle you get a bunch of
people together
are they all gonna suddenly say you know
well i'm actually not american
i'm italian so i'm gonna found like a
little italian republic here and i'll
just get all the italians together by
the way do any of you speak italian
well you know you know my nona did but
she's been dead since
you know 1965. um i can boil spaghetti
though
you know if everybody tries to break
down their own ethnic say i'm going to
revert to my true roots
i don't think my sense is there there
are probably some people in america who
feel that way that like i'm truly this
but i know i live here
but i think most people feel like no i'm
i'm truly american and then the other
problem is
you know how many of us are any of our
are a majority
one ethnicity or the other i mean i'm
three quarters italian which is actually
for a lot of people i know you know you
know
[Music]
more dominated by one particular
ethnicity than a lot of people i was
like
well i'm french and i'm english and you
know maybe i have a little cherokee
indian if you're elizabeth warren you
know
but like they can name six seven
different things and none of them is a
majority so what are you
in that case so in addition to that i
don't
think in my experience this is not the
way americans think in their own heart
but i also think it's just going to be
completely impractical what are we and
then then what are we going to do
so the the karate break the united
states of america
and no the people still alive on the
north american continent must reorganize
themselves
i mean are we going to like try to carve
out little well this is for the italians
but what if you're half italian and what
if you're like
you know and then this one's for the
greeks and this one's for the what
how how's that going to work and then
you know but that's before you even get
into the question of other ethnicities i
don't think people have really
quite thought this through i think their
their hatred civic nationalism for
certain quarters of the right
has just become a hate term a kind of a
swear term and so
rather than trying to think through
practical reality on this
um they just try to find people who they
say adhere to it and therefore those are
the bad guys
and that's really why i wrote the boring
and pedant
oh my god my publisher is going to shoot
me the allegedly boring and pedantic
chapter two because i think all this
stuff has to be thought through
and i'd rather provoke a bunch of people
to write back at me that i was wrong it
was terrible but it forced them to start
thinking about it
then just leave these questions out
lying there i have been involved in
politics
more intensely than my life in the last
five years i wrote a book called
democrat to deplorable i was a lifelong
obama or a lifelong democrat voter obama
voter
around 2014 2015 i saw all these
writings on the wall
i supported trump i wrote a book all
about it why and i see
so many echoes uh for mine is more of
like on the ground the stories of people
who had the same transformative
experience and then yours is sort of
coming at it from a historical and a
high level view
but one of the things that i
consistently struggled with
i'm half irish half ashkenazi my family
came here late 19th
early 20th century i feel 100 american
um i hear the magic dirt arguments or
counter arguments i hear people's
trashing
civic nationalism back in 2016 we had
you know
more unsavory people in the coalition
stressing ethno divisions and whatnot
and and i still haven't
zeroed down and been able to succinctly
say
what is this american consciousness that
that we
that is uniquely american and is it an
idea or
is it a heritage or is it a history or
is it language
and so for me that chapter was really
pertinent and fantastic and i think it's
a key
argument in sort of forming this
anti-globalist
neoliberal neoconservative
so you know the iconoclasm of 2020 where
we're going to rename everything and
tear down statues and you know we're
going to
kind of do what um you know what is an
iconoclastic somebody who goes into
churches and he
busts up the art because it's uh uh in
his
religious uh puritanical view offensive
to god
that beautiful you know it offends the
commander against graven images
that's the idea um okay
i have i have no no strand of dna in me
that's present in north america before
uh 1888 not and yet i revere george
washington as if he's the father of my
country
now to a strict ethno-nationalist he
would say that i suffer from false
consciousness or something
right oh you can't claim that but you i
can claim garibaldi
even though i wasn't born in italy i
didn't grow up speaking italian i had to
teach myself to read italian so that i
could learn machiavelli
and i love visiting italy it's great
it's fun i like the food the
architecture
but i don't feel at home there i don't
feel italian there
now if if you know my life went sideways
in some way and i had to flee
right but you only there were places you
could end up um
uh you know i like the food i like the
tailoring
there's a lot of things like the wine
there's a lot of things i like about it
but
like that that kind of persistent
and the other the other point too that i
would make so again
i i feel only loyal to america i feel
only loyal
to americans i am inspired by american
heroes and
and heritage and the past as if it's my
history
i guess yes there's something um
irrational about that in a certain way
but i'd have to say why like
just because somebody was born in italy
um
you know does that
legitimize being say proud of
michelangelo
where i was born in america but i can't
be proud of george washington
because my dna doesn't trace to 1776
there but if my dna traced to
yeah it's it's a kind of weird argument
that i i don't get that i don't think
adds up i don't think i'm stating this
precisely but what they want to say is
well you're you're an alien well
i guess then everybody isn't i mean
if you go in that direction you're
feeding into the left wing line of
thought which is that america is
illegitimate right so if we all have to
be ethno-nationalists
well then um what's so magical about
getting you know getting on a boat from
you're coming to
america but those people are okay
because they're with the american well
why did you leave it why aren't you
english
right well i'm i'm mayflower stock so i
can be american but you can't because
you your ancestors came later
right well why you then that means
you're english you should be loyal to
that not to this
there only is america because a bunch of
people came here and made america
okay and we the reason why this confuses
people
is because you know we saw it happen
in in in in the modern age when
there were much more complete records
and so on i could ask the same question
about so what makes a
when does an english person become an
english person right there's britons on
the british isle
then the romans come then they
intermarry are we are we english yet
why does it why are why are the
anglo-saxons called anglo-saxons saxony
is in germany it's because a bunch of
people from northern europe come over
and struggle
are they english then you get the norman
conquest in 1066.
are we have we gotten there yet now from
that point on
until the mass migrations following
world war ii the english population was
very very stable
it's basically the same there was no
almost zero net immigration
and you know a little bit here and there
but very very very stable
but but englishness somehow is banged
together over the course of
a thousand years um without
an obvious migratory movement that you
get from northern europe to the united
you know to the north american continent
the founding in the united states and of
course
without a signing ceremony this is what
confuses people so they think like
um well that's the natural way to do it
well if that's the natural way to do it
and the only way to do it in this way is
illegitimate then you've sort of bought
the left-wing argument that no that
there shouldn't be an american no one
from europe should ever come to america
right if if your ethnic status is the
thing
then then both the puritans and the
cavaliers they're
they're just english and they should
never have left right and the other
thing that bothers me that i find
inc consistent about this argument is
people say no no
um the tradition is the only thing we
have to get back to tradition
all right fair enough i'm not against
tradition i'm actually pro tradition
in a lot of ways if it's a good
tradition
but then that gets you into the whole
philosophical question of how do you
evaluate tradition you have to have a
philosophical framework right
plato and aristotle would say because
there's an idea of the good and i can
evaluate anything in the light of that
just because it's old doesn't mean it's
good necessarily but all right
or bad or bad mystery yeah right
um uh well we have to get back to
tradition okay well the american
tradition is fighting the revolution
the american tradition is the
declaration of independence the american
tradition is the constitution and the
northwest ordinance and the bill of
rights
and all of these things so in the name
of tradition are we supposed to reject
our tradition
we're americans we're for tradition but
my god we really do hate the revolution
which gave birth to this country
and we really do hate the fundamental
charters of our liberties which are too
abstract and enlightenment
you know we're supposed to so what
tradition are we supposed to go back to
some medieval tradition
i'm very sympathetic to this argument
they haven't not sorted this out and i'm
sure there's a lot of people listening
right now
who are saying aha you know
can i use like a semi-bad language on
this podcast
yeah dude go ahead he's a right and
he's a sibnet
we knew it all along i like you know
have at it but rather than
i would i would ask people who want to
make that argument
buy the book i could use the money but
leave that aside read
chapter 2 with care and see if you can
give me an
actual point-by-point reputation of it
because i'd love to read it
by these other arguments over the years
even as i am convinced
by critiques from people to my right
about i've been very convinced by
critiques to people from my way about
about the myriad problems of
you know let's say post-1960s america
indeed and i'm very sympathetic to these
arguments i'm with you
for me personally i i'm settling or not
just yet but on a
even though you you throw it out the civ
nap perspective it's
it's it's what i've got to hang on to
and i believe that it has value and
worth and i
i can't it's thought experiment i mean
this is kind of similar to something i
already said but i'll make it really
blunt now
anyway okay thought experiment
just suppose whatever something happens
i mean things happen states collapse it
does happen in human history i say this
the beginning of chapter seven
to pretend like human possibilities that
have bedeviled mankind since the birth
of the species are now behind us forever
because we've solved these problems is
the height of stupidity
so yes for whatever reason it could be
the left's fault it could be the right's
fault it could be a meteor strike it
could be bad luck it could be whatever
the government collapses we're all still
alive we find ourselves somewhere let's
say you and i
and ten thousand other people are
are the residents of some small town in
southern illinois i'm just picking this
out of my hat and
there's no government anymore we see no
signs of the feds no signs of the state
we have to organize we got to make sure
we got the water flowing
the electricity is on that we're growing
food that we have a police force
and that we're maintaining public order
and doing all the things that you need
to do to have
human life we do that and then you know
but we got
you know none of we don't share a common
ethnic identity
right but we share basic interests
we're all physically proximate um we are
speaking to one another in the same
language
and we all kind of grew up in a similar
tradition of what politics is supposed
to be in a similar culture and we kind
of can understand each other
right are we gonna again start
squabbling with one another and be like
well you're a quarter english and you're
at this and then you're a tenth that and
you know
and let's sort are we gonna say we're
gonna get together first we're just
gonna try to
stay alive and self-organize right then
we're going to see
what's going on beyond our borders but
eventually we're going to re-establish
a state on this land aren't we let's go
if aristotle is right
then we will human beings will do that
the state collapses
um they will come back to first it will
be spontaneous order then they will come
back together and there will be formal
order
and when we create that formal order on
what basis are we going to do it
we're going to make a social compact the
same way the founders made a social
compact in 1776
and it was if you're with us you know
you can stay
if you don't like it there's canada
right where the loyalists go or you can
go back across the atlantic but if you
if you want to be in the compact and we
want you then you can stay
and the membership in the compact will
be defined and maybe we will come up
with a new name maybe we will call
ourselves the post-americans or maybe we
will call ourselves the
the whatever you know the jackians right
but
then we will have that then we will have
that new identity and that new identity
will be in part
forged by the struggle and the effort
that goes into creating this new thing
the same way the american identity was
in part
forged by the struggle in creating their
new thing
amen to that i used to train muay thai i
was an amateur muay thai fighter
and the guys on my fight team we went
through grueling
10 and 12 week fight camps three four
five times
and the bonds that we formed going
through that experience and doing that
thing and making that achievement
all that exertion bonds will last
forever i haven't seen some of those
guys in five years i see them the next
day and it's like we're
best buddies so like the the achievement
uh and courage demonstrative acts of
courage and collective achievement
certainly bind people together
this is a conversation that i think we
can continue on much
much longer but i want to move on a
little bit more
where what is the american regime today
like what are we facing today because
let's talk about the scenario
let's talk about what could happen and
then let's talk about what's gonna
happen yeah i mean the regime we face
today is a kind of
oligarchic neoliberal alliance between a
permanent bureaucracy
and big corporations the media
and universities you know this is
chapter three
is is i explain how we're governed um
uh it has a veneer of democracy because
we hold elections every four years for
president every six percent
but the the elections fundamentally
don't change things
trump's election changed more than any
election in the past
probably two generations at least one
generation but
it's also demonstrated the uh difficult
extent to which
or the extent which is very difficult
for someone from outside the system who
ran against the system and who's
fighting the system to change it from
the inside
um the power that the bureaucracy and
all these other power centers have is
just so overwhelming
that it's really hard to get them to do
what you wanted to do as i sort of made
this point about
when i was talking about bolton earlier
you know he was good at getting the
the national security bureaucracy to do
what
he wanted it to do um you know whether
whether what he wanted in a given moment
is something we should all desire is
another question
uh so
it's we're moving toward a kind of just
managerial
state where people don't have much of a
say it would be one thing
you know liberty is uncommon throughout
human history and it would be one thing
not to have liberty but to have a state
that was ruling for the mostly for the
common good
and that left you alone or that actually
helped you but
you know we've increasingly have a state
that and i i just got to be completely
clear that i'm not blaming any of this
on donald trump
no this is the regime donald trump
inherited when he became president and
that he's been pushing back against and
continues to push back against
but that it's that you know as one man
with a limited number of allies in the
federal government
on a bureaucracy and it's not just the
government he has to face the entire
federal government
and every other power center in the
country
it increasingly doesn't rule and have
for a long time hasn't ruled for the
common good it rules for the private
good
of a handful of people and institutions
and it's also increasingly vindictive
and getting more so 2020 has
demonstrated that and
i really worry the direction the
democratic party and the left has taken
that
if and when they retake power they will
be even
more vindictive um
the rhetoric and the actions that we've
seen out of a lot of these people this
year they've really
as i wrote the book you know i i wrote
several passages about left-wing
vindictiveness
in this book and in my last book this
little tiny i'll just hold it with
people
this was called after the flight 93
election it's a very short
kind of crisis if you want to understand
claremontism in one lesson by that
um i as i wrote i thought i understood
the motivations of the left but as i
tried to explain it i thought wow this
sounds
really harsh no one's going to believe
that they're this bad
in a way 2020 kind of uh helped me out
on that
they just came out and ripped the mask
and said we're this bad
if anything anton didn't go far enough
in describing how
fundamentally malevolent and hateful we
are i think that's probably true i think
a lot of us i know i've
i have been doxed by antifa i've been
fired for being a racist in a nazi
been banned from coaching little league
because i've supported trump in
northwest d.c
like i have been through the ringer
scene at all and yet i still
haven't like gone fully 100 cynical
slash accepting
of how malevolent and vindictive
uh the left is and how and how much more
it's even progressing
day by day literally right now yeah i
mean all of this has been latent for a
long time
they've just had the self-discipline and
maybe the self-knowledge to know
that you know we can't we can't show our
true face to the american people it's
too radical
uh it'll give us and something you know
once the dam broke in 2020 they
you know all that it's like it's like
somebody who's just feeling pent up rage
forever and ever and ever but they
keep it under control or base barely
under control because if they scream you
know
and then finally they just snap one day
and then they let it all out i think
that's what happened to 2020.
do you do you think that uh there well
we didn't get we didn't get through all
the various elements of america's regime
today but
there is a revolutionary feel of what's
happening right now an
insurgency right like a weird
revolutionary feel though because it's
it's it's a friend of mine said this i
think he's exactly right
others have compared it to the cultural
revolution now it's called
66 to 76. um
but that is more precise than most
people who say it realized because what
the cultural revolution was it wasn't an
anti-regime revolution it regime
using its worst and most
psychopathic elements to punish those
elements of the society that hadn't gone
along enough with the program so we are
going through a kind of revolution but
it's not like the french revolution
where the old order above is toppled
from below
this is the top using the bottom to
attack the middle which it finds its
continued existence uh and a front
so the revolution is against the middle
yeah
it's against the last remnants of the
old american order it's a kind of in a
way a cleanup operation we're gonna
you know if there's still people who i
then self-identify as american we're
gonna
come we're gonna get you we're gonna at
least have i mean you know so far you
know no gulags i mean we've had some
street
killings but i think it's plenty bad
enough
that it's now considered perfectly
acceptable to dox people get them fired
make them unemployable
and essentially ruin i mean when you
think this through like okay well you're
a racist therefore
you should never be able to work again
if i can't ever work again how am i
supposed to ever eat again
right i mean are we is you know
effective starvation through deprivation
of resources the goal here
are we gonna somebody gonna now they'd
say oh that's crazy we've never argued
for that but implicitly they have
right if you dock somebody and
make this argument that they're
fundamentally evil person and then you
hound all employers if they ever manage
to get another job or
you know call prospective employers and
make sure no one will talk to them how's
this person supposed to earn a living
how are they supposed to have friends
you know and in britain the national
health service which everybody pays for
with their tax
say dollars of course pound uh with
their tax pounds
um we won't treat people whom we deem as
racist
or xenophobic or homophobic or whatever
right so what do we do if
we say somebody's a bad person do we
just they go to the doctor
i'm i'm very sick sorry you're a bad
person just go outside and die
right this is sick evil stuff it seems
it is i would do a slight reframe on
that though
you did address earlier what others have
called the cathedral or the blue church
the amalgamation of the universities and
the bureaucracies and the elites and the
finance
world and the tech world that is that's
the establishment because they're with
the uniparty they're with the bush
clinton obama bush
you know biden cohort it's like trump is
the insurgent
the reds are the trump insurgency we are
the revolutionaries
trying to actually take back this the
state right
and and all the institutions which have
been completely co-opted and converged
so to me it is the state using its own
power to try to beat us into submission
and uh you know trump has been fighting
uh an insurgency
you saw firsthand where he is resisted
within the government itself which
existed within the bureaucracy
yeah it's hard enough to get anything
done when you're a noob anyway but when
everybody
is actively working against you too so
that's sort of the lens in which i see
the revolution which is ironic
given that you know we're people that
support the founding and the founding
documents and
all the values laid out there how are
how are we the insurgents
you know uh how how are we the
insurgents in this scenario when we
actually are the ones carrying the
flag of the nation the regime has been
effectively replaced
yeah you know the it was a
it was a slow process i guess you could
say i don't know
was it 50 years was it 30 years but the
regime was effectively replaced i would
urge your readers all to also to check
out chris caldwell's book
the age of entitlement it's kind of a
bad title because it doesn't exactly
reveal what's inside the book
but his main thesis is that um
the 1964 civil rights act and the
following
and all the enabling legislation and all
the stuff and the decrees and things
that came over
are a de facto second constitution
that's replaced the first constitution
and that all of the elites hue to the
second and ignore or despise the first
and so the insurgency is being fought by
people on behalf of the fir in a sense
on behalf of the first constitution
but from a position of of weakness of
relative weakness
indeed and in fact you know as reading
claremont
and just seeing it's established
competing systems of justice right and
this is this is like one of the most
fundamental schisms that we have is
you know competing notions of justice is
that
a theme that you you know support and
carry on i mean you did reference called
well quite a bit in the book
i i i i definitely
um push that notion competing notions of
justice but i put it a little
differently i just say look this is the
design of the american government
this is how it's supposed to work this
is the fundamental basis of
political legitimacy as the founders
understood it and of
uh you know the moral dignity of
individual
humans and why we have rights and how
we're supposed to be treated
and this is the way we're governed now
and it doesn't look anything like that i
mean
in in many ways it's the opposite
and well go ahead what are the what are
the the tools of this regime that's
taken over
you know you talk about the narrative
the megaphone and the
game is the main tool it's not certainly
not the only tool propaganda
uh forcing out only one message uh
um and blaring it at 100 and
however many decibels through every
channel that they control
and uh drowning out or actively
suppressing
counter narratives counter claims and
punishing people who state counter
claims
that's even worse even worse than
censorship is the punishment of
individual
dissenters now you know
i repeat i think this is kind of an
important thing i mean the only logical
place like cancellat culture
leads is starvation right
because think about it from the leftist
perspective you're evil you're racist
you shouldn't be able to have a job
you shouldn't be able to earn a living
well then why should you be able to eat
it and
in any way what in what practical sense
will you be able to eat if you can't
earn any money and the leftist would say
oh anton's just
that's a reduction out of him he's being
crazy it's like but wait you just said
this guy should never be able to work
again
so how's he supposed to live for the
rest of his life how does he
eat how's he supposed to get medical
care and then they just start yelling at
you
or they ignore you but i'm trying to
draw out all these logical
um where their rhetoric and principles
logically lead because i think they lead
to incredibly scary
and evil places yeah and you know
there's a real world examples of guys
you know
having their worst moments caught on on
stream
it's the number one result for their
google search they can't find jobs for
two years and then they're dead in their
car and their families wondering
where they are there's concrete examples
of that i fortunately
lived through exactly this thing antifa
and their mob came to my employer
tried to say i was a nazi i worked for
an education regulator in dc i was a
charter school executive for many years
and i worked for the regulator in dc i
was a senior finance manager there
and it's a hundred percent woke hundred
percent social justice warrior critical
race theory
all top to bottom and so the minute
somebody said
oh this guy's a racist nazi i mean it
was i was done
they they fired me specifically even
stating things that i had said and so
they're firing me in violation of my
first member rights all kinds of stuff
so
i was fortunate because i've been able
to tap into this new technology and this
new
environment this new world but not
everybody is like that and not
everybody's gonna have that opportunity
so
there will be a growing army of exiles i
worked for a number of years in
corporate america and i could see it
trending that way
and i i didn't you know i all i can say
is
i don't i don't know that i'd be able to
tolerate it now
i think we just have to leave if you are
that the way the way you've seen some of
these corporations
go so pedal to the floor awoke i mean
they had always they've been trending
that way but like 2020 they all just
decided
we're all in and i i know
i would probably just have to if i if i
didn't get fired for something
i'd said in the past uh i would have
just had to walk away because i just i
think i would find the environment
intolerable uh it's stifling
dehumanizing
uncomfortable horrible etc for sure
um the the wokeness i've seen comes
at least initially it came from within
the universities and then those people
graduate
and then they become the new people in
the corporations and what i saw at least
my perception is that the corporations
bent to the will of the
the young kids thinking that's what they
needed to recruit
but then this corporate woke alliance
of 2020 that has been so pronounced
with just hundreds of millions of
dollars
i i cover the riots in washington dc i
go down there at 16th and 8th street and
the friggin buildings are draped and
giant black lives
matter banners on a street with black
lives matter
painted on it with the name changed to
black lives matter plaza
and they're beating war drums and
they're in a formation
fighting the police with the black lives
matter flag flying in the background
how was it always there did i miss
something but
it seems in this year the money the real
money the real
money is there how did that happen and
how do we how do we break it up
i talked about this this morning with
somebody and it's not a new thought i've
heard it
people express it before
as recently as 2010 and maybe even as
recently as 2015 you would hear people
in you know corporate america in
corporate manhattan
say you know the real tragedy is that
these universities are turning out these
these spun up super woke students they
don't learn anything and then when they
meet the real world boy
they're gonna they're gonna find it's
hard you know
hard rowing and they're not gonna be
able to make it no it's because these
these are people like in their 40s and
their 50s or whatever and it was
different when they came in like they
had to
defer to authority they got worked
really hard if they didn't do well
they'd get bounced out or they didn't
get promoted and stuff
and so they thought it would be the way
it was when they started out in their
careers and
the to their shock the exact opposite
happened the
indeed all of the kids got into these
roles in the media and in finance and in
corporations
and the people above them in the in the
management chain
showed no courage whatsoever they just
caved immediately
and now this is again one of those
things that i i
suspect or at least wonder whether you
know if it can't go on forever it won't
right your job as a corporation is to
make money which means you need to be
focused on the core mission and on the
bottom line and all of these things
so you know how long how long can woke
capital keep the stuff going if they're
not focused on the core mission if
they're not focused on basic competence
if they're not focused on what they're
there to do and i'm making money
i i don't know um you never want to bet
against these guys
look at how much they've managed to
accomplish for themselves how much power
they've managed to accrue
already but i just have to think an
economy
this um wacky
this hasn't happened before i you know i
know something about history you know
you know i try to look back trying to
think of a time when like the all the
major centers of the economy
were not merely focused on something
other than their core mission but
we're focused on things that
legitimately tear at the social fabric
on a daily basis
and how long can that possibly last for
them and for the society itself
it's just hard to imagine that this is
like a truly new order of the ages that
can last a couple centuries or longer
i mean i wonder if it can last a couple
decades or longer well
i think it lasts as long as the
government in power is not focusing on
antitrust so i think that i i believe
that this is this is like anti-trust
play it's an alignment
to diminish the power of the federal
government deliver to legitimize the
federal government
and therefore the corporations are
aligned with the black lives matter
activists and antifa
because they both want to see
diminishment of federal power and
and authority and and whatever um and
and
it's working out for them at this point
so until those
there are reasons to doubt that too in
that there are so many ways that federal
power
serves big corporations that uh you know
that they've been able to essentially
co-opt federal power and use it
to you know how much foreign policy is
conducted essentially to serve corporate
interests now so do they want to see
federal power
it's not like the federal government
ever barely think of instances where the
federal government of its own accord
without being forced to by the president
does anything
against corporate power but the other
but the
the simpler question for me is you know
so i worked at a bank
right the essence of banking is you loan
somebody money
you loan a company or somebody money at
a certain rate of interest because you
think you will
make a profit off that interest he will
invest the money and spend it wisely and
be able to pay it back with the interest
and to do that you have to do very
careful risk assessment and analysis of
the company or whatever you're loaning
to and
knowing that a certain percentage of
your loans are going to go bad and
you're not going to get your money back
you bake that into your overall
assessment and as long as
you know you have a you win more than
you lose or you win sufficiently more
than you
you make money if everything becomes
about wokeness
and not about again the core mission how
long are these firms going to be able to
make money it doesn't matter what their
relationship with the federal government
is at that point
they'll just crash because they don't
know what they're doing anymore it's
like if
i run a restaurant and i'm cooking very
well people are coming in and then i
decide
everything is going to be about social
justice in this restaurant everything
we're going to be the wokest restaurant
in the world and the food starts to suck
and those waiters are terrible and you
know
you you wait 30 minutes for your
appetizer and it's lame or they bring
you the wrong thing
and so on after a while you're gonna
aren't you gonna go out of business i
mean do the laws of gravity somehow no
longer apply i don't know i
i just don't i find it
hard to believe that they can keep this
going indefinitely
yeah when i say diminishment of federal
power with respect to the corporations i
mean sort of like the co-opting of the
federal power for their own interest
that's definitely happened yeah and and
so
it it a weaker federal government
benefits both black lives matter and the
corporations in that regard and
uh to listeners you know you guys know
i've recommended matt stoller's book
goliath you should check that out
uh really lays out the way that both
parties have come together and supported
the neo-liberal world order
and served the corporations at the
expense of the middle class matt stoller
somebody i think
if you haven't talked to him he you and
he echo a lot of the similar things and
uh he he i think is somebody who is is
very disappointed with the democrats
um and is is looking to make changes and
saying a lot of the same things
that we're saying um moving on a little
bit
let's talk about immigration
briefly yeah that's a fairly long
chapter look it's a
i wrote two years ago in the washington
post an op-ed
i wrote two and they'll never ever
publish me again um but
the first one was just saying why do we
need more people and this is like
instead of a an 800 word why do we need
more people this is like 20 000 words on
why we don't need more people
but to me so i take the founder's point
on immigration
there's social compact the existing
members of the compact have the right to
invite
into the compact or exclude from the
compact anybody they want
um that by when i say exclude meaning
exclude potential new interests they
don't have the right to
kick people out unless they've committed
some kind of crime irrelevant right
so we have the right the founders
thought this from the beginning we have
the right and they
um welcomed immigrants when they thought
that made sense and then they didn't
when they didn't
same thing throughout our history we got
to the point because of the civil rights
revolution of the 60s
that it came to be understood implicitly
understood in
liberal america in the left-wing mind
and according to the second constitution
that every person alive on the planet
fundamentally has the right to emigrate
to america
and um nobody in america has the right
to say no
that it's racist or it's unjust or it's
something if you say no
to anyone so i say
immigration is a policy like any other
and
the lens through which you see it is
what are the needs of the existing
citizenry
and at 330 million right now with
with a with a massive wave of
immigration over the last
well since 1965 so 55 years and with
very very high unemployment especially
and with a a labor market that's been
beaten down in part by
high immigration since at least since
the early 70s
uh wage stagnation and so on um
we don't need just the united states for
a million reasons
doesn't need more people right now and
we can revisit that later
as a country as a citizen body later and
say
all right maybe we need more people in
year x or y or whatever but i think
right now
it's plainly obvious to me that we don't
it's plainly obviously
insane to take in a million i mean that
numbers are down under trump but they're
still
high much higher than they need to be to
keep taking in people when
we you know we had i think unemployment
peaked during the covey year at
15 or 16. now it's down to about 10
and falling so that's good but what i
also fear is that you know as soon as it
gets to
the the oligarchies are saying oh i
can't get anybody to do these jobs
anymore
well actually i've seen all kinds of
stories about
the success of the of of the immigration
restriction
and that people are hiring americans
again and and you know what at higher
wages
and a business of course doesn't want to
hire anyone at a higher wage but you
know as an american citizen
i'm delighted even if it means i have to
pay marginally more for
whatever product i'm paying more for
yeah you know consumer price index is
not
the highest good or gdp growth
uh per capita that's for sure i did see
some interesting stories about uh like
i want to say it was like a fishing town
in maine that didn't have the
immigrant labor and who did they hire
kids
teenagers oh my god that's impossible to
imagine in california
but i um actually there's one exception
which i'll get to in a second but when i
was a kid in california
uh everybody i knew worked the summers
oh yeah high school everybody
and that became impossible because all
those jobs got um
um taken by immigrants you know one
one of the big exceptions if you've ever
in california especially southern
california but the chain is now all over
the state and in a few other states it's
called in and out burger it's a
privately owned fast food
chain and um
uh you know owned by a christian family
and
and when you go there teenagers work
there now white teenagers hispanic
blacks every but the difference they're
real kids from the local schools and one
of the reasons is they pay above minimum
wage
they always have paid above minimum wage
and
nobody else no none of the other fast
food chains pay above the minimum wage
and it's one of the reasons why the
service is so much better
snappier smiling welcome and it's just
boom boom boom right on the money and
hey the
the family that owns that they're really
rich
which suggests to me there's a way to
hire local people
to hire american citizens to pay a
decent above minimum wage wage and still
make a lot of money
yeah yeah i agree with that i worked i
worked as early as sixth grade
delivering newspapers i woke up every
morning delivered newspapers
cut grass shoveled lawns got a job at
the mall when i was like 14.
uh even even thinking of my dog my
daughter's 15 now
um maybe i'm doing her disservice but
like just the notion of she's like i'm
gonna go get a job at the mall i'm gonna
be gone four nights a week or whatever
that like
even strikes me as a little bit crazy
but i know what good it did for me it
certainly made me a hustler
there's no question about that in the
school year but
they just definitely kicked my butt to
do it in the summers
yeah and of course you know in those
days like uh
i wanted the money but it was a freer
time it wasn't like now where everything
is scheduled and especially in cove a
year but
you know kind of after a certain point
you can get a car or even ride your bike
and go where you want it and it was it
was a freer time
i wanted the money that's exactly i know
my dad's
my dad would say to me why do you want
to work you're going to work the rest of
your life and i was like okay give me
the money and he's like no
okay i'm getting and i'm getting a job
i'm getting a job
all right so immigration is something do
you have you had an
evolution on that perspective or has
this been your your party line for
a while um of the big trump positions
it's the one that attracted me to trump
exists the one that was most aligned
with is that i've held the longest but i
have you know
i went through an evolution on that
question myself
and mostly it was over you know i left
california
for good that is i've been back you know
many hundreds of times on trips but i
left it
as a resident for good in 1998
and uh or nine something like that and
not thinking about immigration and i
mean i thought about it in 94 because of
the pete wilson
ballot initiative on uh welfare for
illegal aliens
supported that thinking okay that'll
help fix the problem which
it might you know it might have i mean
no less than
hyper-libertarian economist um
milton friedman who i actually met a few
times uh used to say
you can either have open borders or a
welfare state but not both
right so okay if we're gonna if we're
not gonna do much about the border you
can't have
you know a welfare state on this scale
because it acts as a magnet
um i left the state not really thinking
about it
and and it started to think about it as
i would go home more and
it's it i guess if you're there maybe
the change is more
imperceptible but if you're gone and you
come back and you're gonna come
everything looks just kind of a little
more subtly different
at every six month or 12-month interval
and i started to think
this is not this is looking really
different in a lot a lot a lot of ways
and the more i studied it the more i
thought
yeah this isn't working and then i at a
certain point i realized that the main
reason california became
not the only but the main reason
california became a one-party
democratic blue state was demographic
change in two sentences one is
the continued influx of of legal and
illegal immigration
but also the pressure that that put on
the old california
middle class to just leave you know the
california
base that was the stronghold for nixon
and reagan
elected you know uh reagan governor
twice and nixon was the first president
of california
there's just barely a remnant of them
anymore because they they either they
got priced out
or it got so crowded or their industries
closed
or or were outsourced or were squeezed
out by
you know tech money and these kinds of
things there
that that california that entire sort of
civilization in a way that i grew up in
is is basically gone now the only people
left
from old california are either people
just sort of hanging by a thread
um or i describe this in chapter one
there are people who are lucky enough to
inherit
a house from their parents and inherit
the prop 13
assessment so they don't have to pay the
sky high property taxes
or they're people who just kind of made
it like you know maybe you grew up in
lodi but you went off to berkeley and
then you got a job in san francisco and
you know hey
you know it's like the old american
story
there's a lot of people you'll meet you
could go off to some fancy college who
are from some
kind of small lower middle class town
that make it good and never go home
and i'm sure there are people in in
coastal california
who fit that category that grew up in
some kind of you know more backwater
part of the state
but made it to the 101 corridor and now
are rich enough that they don't have to
think about leaving but boy for every
one of those that i know i know another
three four or five who just
got to a certain point and i'm out yeah
so california is a little bit of our
future if we
allow this dual constitution
competing systems of justice woke mob
you know take over all of our
institutions
push for mass immigration have no
healthy borders
and you know one thing i wanted to
mention about healthy borders i did a
podcast with joe norman
who is a complex systems scientist and
he and i were talking about how every
system
whether it's a computer system a
biological system ecological system
has natural borders that have some sort
of almost
sentience right like they they operate
they they decide what comes in and what
doesn't
to preserve the health of the entity
and to think that we don't have that
established
around our physical nation or even
ideologically or even spiritually
is bizarre to me and it's it's a it's a
it's a recipe for complete
disintegration if there's no
other there is no you right yeah i
um one of the first things that when
i've really started to
i mean trump got my notice from the
escalator ride it was you know a huge
deal
and everybody was talking about it but
again i just thought he's not he's not
really running so
i care when he said i don't remember
exactly at what point he said this so if
i have the chronology wrong i
apologize but when he said if we don't
have a border we don't have a country
i thought that may be the wisest thing
any presidential candidate has said in
my lifetime
or since and it's it sounds so
tautologically obvious
which it is the fact that he had to say
it
because conventional wisdom is so
against something so basic like that
and had the courage to say it and what i
especially loved about it is
he didn't feel the need to go into
intellectual contortions to explain
why this was the right position to him
it was just
self-evident yeah just right from the
gut
all right that's my guy yeah well
it is true and we need more trump as you
say
there are no existing problems that more
trump
can't solve i love that piece that you
published
a few months ago or recently um
but let's talk about as we as we sort of
start to wind this down here let's let's
talk about
what if we don't do anything and then
what do we need to do
uh if we don't do anything then we get i
think
likely we get one of the outcomes of
chapter six or seven so basically
chapter six says
what if present trends continue in
particular what if you know
uh you could get the outcome in chapter
six
if trump is defeated if he's re-elected
and
um you know has an unsuccessful second
term or even if he's re-elected and has
a successful second term but then is
defeated
and then a successor is defeated in 2024
and the left gets back in power and they
basically erase
traces of the trumpet to right now so
basically what chapter six is
what if we could take a time machine
back to 2015 elect hillary clinton and
just start implementing the democratic
agenda
or it doesn't even have to be hillary
whoever it is yeah you know
for however long he lasts kamala harris
any of them what does that look like and
i theorize it out
a version of that was published on
american greatness um
last friday under the title another
happy title
uh a tyranny perpetual and universal
question mark
this is the phrase tyranny perpetual
universal comes from
the introduction to leo strauss's uh
1949 book
on tyranny um which i explained at the
at the end and then chapter seven and
then i and then so the second half of
the first half of chapter six says this
is what that would look like and the
second half says
here are the reasons to doubt that they
couldn't pull it off for very long
you know i had a conversation um
no we mentioned beatty earlier right
yeah darren
former white house right or i was
talking to darren
and we were sort of debating like how
long do you think if they got everything
they wanted how long could they keep it
going
and darren took the position as i recall
this conversation
a pretty long time and i was like i
don't think so i don't know i don't
think so so in that conversation he was
a pessimist and i was the
although i think i say in a way an
optimist because if they can't keep it
going
it won't end happily it'll crash in a
bad way now there may be good outcomes
on the other side but then there's going
to be a period of
not good all right can i can i just step
in there for one second
john robb who uh is a technologist a
futurist an analyst network analyst
he's described a situation called what
he calls the long night
and that is when the convergence of
technology
ai and sort of tyrannical
you know ideology that that if it if it
all happens
soon enough or at the right time that it
could just be
a switch right that we no longer have
access to bank and we no longer have
assets to jobs
internet communication whatever whatever
you're completely tracked and monitored
at all times
and there's may not actually be a way to
resist that
um is that you know yeah you've had an
idea you've heard them
relentlessly i that would have that
would require technology
mixed and perhaps mixed with
pharmaceuticals or something
to fundamentally change human nature in
a way that i wonder if it's possible
right
because at a minimum let's say you could
you could track everybody all the time
and inspire fear into everybody all the
time
i still think if human nature remains
human
then what you'll see is just this
massive drop in productivity and the
incentive to do anything or be anything
and the system will be
in a sense self-correcting you know what
i mean am i am i making sense like if
so you know the the the soviets there
was an old joke from the soviet union
about how the soviet economy worked or
how payroll worked the worker said
we pretend to work they pretend to pay
us right
everybody knew that they were producing
nothing and earning nothing
if you get to that point where nobody
has any incentive there's no joy in
their life
they know they're completely impressed
they don't get to own anything keep
anything they don't get to create
anything
they're gonna have no energy they're not
gonna put their energy into anything and
then and then what happens to
you know as a prosaic matter i think i
ask this yeah
this gets to the second half of chapter
six which is reasons to doubt
reasons to doubt they can keep this
going if they come up with a system like
that i mean just as a basic point
who's going to build the gulf stream
airplanes and who's going to fix them
and who's going to fly them and who's
going to maintain them
yeah we're going to have people
competent enough and who have enough
who get enough out of their lives to put
effort into this or is everybody
just going to be like i i know that the
game is rigged and defeated against me
so okay
i'll take my pill and go play my video
game in which case
there won't be gated estates anymore or
there might be the ruins of gated estate
somewhere but no one will be able to
maintain them or live in them which
means the oligarchs
won't be able to enjoy their spectacular
wealth this is what's one of those
things that i think
sounds implausible to me for that reason
yeah
again never bet against these guys i
mean who thought that
to this point who thought that corporate
america would pledge whatever it was 1.7
billion dollars to black lives matter in
like a week
i didn't think that so anything can
happen
i definitely didn't see that coming
either and unfortunately it's going to
be with us
for a little bit longer so
we don't think it could stay together
the democratic left
possible maybe a little bit maybe a
little bit longer than we think
and then chapter seven is to finally
okay and if it doesn't then what happens
and then what happens well
you know um i think the certainly the
events of 2020 are going to
um accelerate the big sort
in other words if you're a red person
living in a blue state
you're going to leave and maybe vice
versa i think it's going to be more the
former than the latter
but blue areas are going to get bluer
red areas are going to get redder
okay and that'll be mostly peaceful just
moving bands and you know
individual private decisions um
another possibility is that when
that i theorize when the left regains
power
if the left regains power i mean when is
probably a lot more likely than if
uh it's easy to imagine some extremely
zealous ideologue in the white house
like kamala harris or
uh elizabeth warren or aoc you know
bumbling into another ruby ridge type
fiasco
but really provoking something this time
and that provocation could lead to
any number of things and one of my calls
the the uh you know the red state
uh bangla meaning which is a french word
it means kind of a no-go zone i could
imagine
a a kind of passive resistance in red
states where they say okay feds
you you're not you're not coming in here
and you're not doing that here
and um you know the feds
then think you know maybe the these
zealots in the white house think well
i'll send the 80-second airborne in and
crush them and then they
what somebody says well wait a minute
what if we give that order and they
don't follow it or what if we give that
order when we started and that provokes
a greater backlash maybe we should cool
it
and both sides just sort of agree let's
de facto
leave each other alone because we don't
really like one another and neither one
of us has the power to push the other
around too much
and you end up getting a kind of radical
federalism and decentralization
without it either formally being decreed
that's another possibility we see the
beginnings of that already don't we with
uh sanctuary states and cities and
yeah but only from only from the blue
left
we don't see it at all because so far
anytime the reds step out of line the
feds have gone in there and said we will
come and just squash you
i wouldn't push back on that just to
smidge in
virginia last winter and spring there
was the second amendment
uh issue counties banned together west
virginia reaches out
to them so that is an example of a
network
nothing came of that the virginia
legislature still rammed through
all of its anti-gun legislation on a
blue party line vote
and nothing has happened on that so
what i have yet to see is successful red
state
passive resistance to federal
encroachment
now maybe the sys maybe the situation
hasn't gotten
you know bad or dire enough for somebody
to try that yet
and could get there i think another
possibility which we can't really rule
out
uh is the secession or at least the
attempt at secession some people say
well secession could never happen to
which i say maybe maybe not i don't know
but the attempt is much it could
certainly happen
it's it's it's hard to imagine right now
but it's not that hard to imagine in the
near future some state saying i've had
enough
and it's legislature filing a session
resolution
and where it goes from there you know is
gained out in the book uh
you know all the way from a formal
agreement fine go
to wait wait what do you want to stay in
i'll give you that and then they back
down
to a war or an attempt at a war
um and then i talk about
caesarism which is a very specific type
of one-man rule and the possibility that
somebody could take over the country
this is typically
you know caesarism is a thing that has
happened in history and that happens to
failing or failed republics as ours is
certainly
failing on a lot of levels if it hasn't
yet failed i think it could still be
revived but
we have to admit this possibility and
then as i say you know i think we talked
about this kind of at the beginning of
the new polis it could be
possible that the government simply
collapses at some point for whatever
reason some external shock and people
are still alive on the north american
continent
and they have to self-organize and i
could see that self-organization
beginning in small towns and then
becoming leagues of small towns it could
even happen at the state level
and you could see a patchwork of you
know states that is to say sovereign
states on the north american continent
that over time may see their shared
interests so aligned that they
formally joined one another and where
you have maybe you know two or three or
four different
sovereign entities on the north american
continent or or what is now let's put
this way what is now the territory of
the united states
um it's not impossible by the way
um that well i'll leave that out i
actually deliberately cut that from
chapter seven so i won't say that
no that's the juicy bit particular
thought um
and then that chapter closes with the
kind of the darkest
part of the book of all which i it's a
reference to the classical notion of the
cycle of regimes
i won't describe it one one can you know
just buy it and read it
and then chapter eight's my happy ending
right so the there's nothing that
wrong with trump that more trump
wouldn't solve comes from chapter eight
and it's sort of my way of saying look
here's a blueprint for how we can avoid
this if i want to stay together
as a territorial republic in the
currently constituted united states of
america with this population
here's the way we can do it and redress
all the balances of the economy
and it's basically my cut at a trumpet
populist
nationalist program for the 2020s and
beyond
which you know naturally i hope is
implemented to the letter
and that is programmed for that right
why else would you write it
right and in this case this is mock and
attack the elites create a new media
education reform student debt reform
yeah
and possibly even state county
realignment with
the borders i think this is an
interesting one as you talked about you
know west virginia
welcoming i quote somewhere joel kotkin
he's a
i can't remember where he was born but
he's lived in california a long time and
he's a real analyst of california
and cot can in an essay i think from
this year
said the worst thing to be in america
right now
is to be a red a person living in a blue
state
that's me washington dc baby so
there are so many parts of the country
where vast
geographic territory and lots of people
now granted not high population density
but lots of people are completely
dominated by
what you know illinois dominated by
chicago virginia
dominated by the dc suburban counties
and a little bit by richmond and then
the whole rest of it is red
and i think you could see it's like okay
if we want to keep the united states
together let's try a little bit more
federalism
let's let some of those rural counties
in virginia leave the state and join
another
another state maybe we could create some
new states you know there's been a
movement in um
northern california and southern oregon
for years to create the state of
jefferson carve the rural counties of
far north california and southern oregon
and create a new state there's nothing
that says we have to have 50.
the flag has been redesigned before if
we need more stars we can figure out a
way
we figured it out with the admission of
alaska and hawaii you know
i if you're if you're in eastern oregon
right now
paying taxes to the state wouldn't you
be thinking to yourself i think what's
the capital of oregon salem right
you're thinking yourself i don't want to
pay any money whatsoever to support
anarchists burning down portland
if portland wants to eat itself let
portland do it on its own
i want out right whether that means i
join a new state whether it means i join
idaho
maybe eastern washington also wants out
of seattle and they can form the two
together
those two could form a new state i think
there's a lot of possibilities to look
at
that would really lower the temperature
of politics and let people
live differently in the way they want to
live if
the ruling class and the people who hold
all levers of power can show a little
bit of restraint and creative thinking
and let something like this happen
but restraint and the ruling class are
not
concepts that go together much these
days no it's just been an
acceleration of or a deceleration of
restraint i don't know there's probably
a more elegant way to say that
uh the last thing i want to touch on i'm
going to take us out here is
you do at the end a lot of this book is
just singing to me because i've been
working on and writing these issues
about these issues from the ground
i worked in education i've studied k-12
studied secondary i understand
most of the issues going on there title
ix the implementation
of intersectionality throughout our
campuses and into
campus life etc and one of the things
you did mention too was the the war on
on masculinity the one in four rape lies
the
you know i don't i don't think you got
into the wage gap myth but you know
these are
fundamental myths uh that that the left
is
is built upon lies you know absolute
lies and so for me the way i tie this
all together michael is that
you know i started off writing about
masculinity and the lost
sort of sense of masculinity
diminishment the feminization of boys in
america
and i started an organization called the
liminal order and we're we are dedicated
to three values of
masculinity brotherhood and sovereignty
and this is our response
our grassroots response to all the
things outlined in your book
uh and you did suggest that there should
be a new school for boys where they
study great books in the morning
uh trades and guns and guns and fighting
during the
and then fighting at night and uh you
know that that's
basically the spirit of what we've got
going on and i think you're spot on with
that
and uh we're out there making it happen
on a day-to-day basis
with ourselves and with our families and
our communities and so we're very much
aligned here michael i really appreciate
the time that you've taken
guys the the name of the book is right
here
it oh that is the caldwell book uh it's
called this
oh i gotta say it what's that well this
is good too though oh no absolutely you
guys get to call the book as well but
here it is the stakes
america at the point of no return
uh the book is fantastic very well
written it is an
exhortation it's meant to get you up off
your ass and maybe do something
there is a sense of urgency to it i feel
it we all feel it in america today
i appreciate everything that you do and
the work that you've done and your
essays and your books and
your contributions and service to uh our
great country so thank you very much for
your time michael and
uh is there is there anything else that
you'd like to get out there like uh
you got a twitter you gotta you got a
website you got anything like that
too old and just don't have the
personality for social media so i'll
never be on
twitter or facebook or any of them i'm a
long format guy
that's just the way i write excellent so
go get the book guys
uh and for me please follow me on
twitter at jack murphy live check out
the website jackmarphylive.com read the
book democrat to deplorable
and if you're interested in what i said
about the liminal order come check it
out liminal hyphen order dot com
sign up and learn everything you need to
know michael thank you so much
and we are out thank you